All right, let's get talking about virtualization.
Virtualization is when things get really interesting
on the mainframe.
So you've got this machine that is physically very big.
The goal is always to make them smaller and smaller,
but a mainframe actually does have a ton of processors,
memory, and IO in it.
And it's got all the cooling and the power
and the network required to make it run.
So it's big, but that's a physical description.
Again, we're trying to draw this distinction
between physical and logical, right?
So you've got a mainframe.
You've got this big, empty, logical area.
We've defined all the physical stuff.
You've got all these processors, the storage, the IO adapter,
but not formed into anything yet.
So you start grabbing a couple of these processors.
There's a little bit of memory, some connectivity,
a couple of IO adapters.
You start squishing them all together and you say, OK,
this is a new system right here.
I've built a new system out of these physical components.
I've built a logical system here.
And for all intents and purposes, it is a computer.
You can start it up.
You can shut it down.
It runs an operating system.
It has a display.
Well, it's a virtual display.
You have to use some software to look at it,
but it's a computer.
And we call that a logical partition or an L-par.
So building an L-par, it's a lot like having this big,
plastic tub of building blocks, right?
It's nothing built specifically,
but you got all these resources here.
So you can grab some pieces and you start
sticking them together.
And look, I made a boat.
And I'd take some more over here,
start putting them together.
And I've made a house, right?
I can make a car.
And I can keep on going until I've run out of resources.
So I do the same thing with physical resources
on a mainframe to build these L-pars.
Say I've got 16 L-pars, all built on my mainframe.
And some of them are really big with a bunch of processors
and memory and IO, and some of them are really small,
just enough just to run a basic program.
Some have a ton of processors,
but not a lot of memory.
Some have very few processors,
but a ton of IO adapters.
And you can build them like that.
That's kind of the flexibility behind virtualization.
Physically, the mainframe looks the same before
and after you've done all that.
It's just sits there and does its job, it's a mainframe.
But logically, you've created 16 new systems.
And if you told somebody, hey,
check out my system, log into this system I created.
They wouldn't have any way of knowing
that it's an L-par, sitting next to a whole bunch
of other systems within one big physical system,
because it's its own computer, its own system.
You've got one big physical mainframe
and 16 logical servers.
I do wanna talk a little bit more
about resources on the mainframe,
particularly the processors.
There are a whole bunch of processor units, processors,
and a processor can behave in a couple different ways,
depending on how it's configured.
It can be a processor, just like the one
in a desktop computer or a laptop
where it runs the operating system
and helps with applications.
And that's called a CP or a central processor.
You can also have a system assist processor, SAP or SAP,
and an SAP helps link between the CP and the I-O.
So instead of the main processor having to worry
about shuffling data back and forth
and saying, oh, take this byte off of here
and move it over here.
The SAP processor handles all that stuff.
It speeds things up tremendously.
It lets the CP focus on the business application
that's running, not on the stuff in the background.
And then there's the IFL, the integrated facility
for Linux, which is a processor specifically
for running Linux on the mainframe.
Now you can run Linux on a CP processor,
a general purpose one, but the IFL
has special licensing associated with it.
So it's more cost-effective for running Linux.
And then lastly, there's zip processors.
That's Z-I-I-P. For certain workloads,
you can use these zip processors
to offload work to them, stuff like Java runs on zips.
And again, the purpose is to one,
let the main processor offload their work,
and two, enable more cost-effective option for workloads
where it might be hard to predict or contain them.
I mentioned earlier, the I-O adapters.
Now the mainframe has a lot of I-O adapters.
Each one of those wires you're seeing in this picture
right here goes up to an I-O adapter.
And there's even more on the back,
and even more on the other frame.
On the other end, those are connected
to disk storage devices, network adapters,
network attached storage, other mainframes, you name it.
We identify these I-O adapters as channel path identifiers
or chipids.
The chipid is associated with a physical port location,
also called a P-Chid for the physical channel ID,
and a logical subsystem that it's associated with.
The subsystem is the connection between the L-PAR
and the I-O devices, or other L-PARs
that it needs to communicate directly with.
You can put everything into one big subsystem,
or you can create a few logical subsystems within it.
So the chipid, which is the association
between the physical port location and the subsystem,
you can think about it just like being a line between the two,
can be dedicated fully to one L-PAR,
meaning it has full control of it,
or it can be shared between multiple L-PARs.
It can also be unshared and reconfigurable,
meaning that it can be switched from one L-PAR to another,
but only one at a time, since it's a logical connection.
And lastly, a chipid can also be configured as spanned,
which means that it's actually accessed
from partitions from multiple logical channel subsystems.
One last word about virtualization,
that we're gonna take a very logical and physical break.
In addition to hosting operating systems
within L-PARs, there's an operating system
that specializes in virtualization,
called ZVM, or virtual machine.
ZVM is a type one hypervisor,
meaning that it doesn't need to sit on top
of another operating system in order to do its thing.
And within ZVM, you can create hundreds,
thousands of virtual machines.
They all share the resources that the host ZVM system has.
And to the mainframe, it thinks it's just hosting
one big operating system, but within it,
you can run any number of operating systems,
anything that runs on the mainframe runs under ZVM,
including another ZVM.
So that's virtually everything I have to tell you
about virtualization on the mainframe.